<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<root>

    <entry>
        <references>1.1--1.5</references>
        <comment>Meliboeus. You lie at ease and sing of your love: I am driven into exile.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>silvestrem musam</text>
        <references>1.2.1, 1.2.3</references>
        <comment>"woodland song", the woodland being the forest pasture where the shepherds feed their
        flocks.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>tenui avena</text>
        <references>1.2.2, 1.2.5</references>
        <comment>"the slender oat", i.e. the rustic pipe. (So the English pastoral poets speak of "oaten
        stop", "oaten pipe".)</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>tu, Tityre</text>
        <references>1.4.4--1.4.5</references>
        <comment>Notice the pretty artifice, whereby he begins and ends with Tityrus.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>lentus</text>
        <references>1.4.6</references>
        <comment>"at ease"</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>deus</text>
        <references>1.6.3</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">deus</span> is Octavianus. To speak of Octavianus as a god to whom lambs will be sacrificed is
        at this date probably only a half playful exaggeration; but afterwards of course the emperor
        Augustus was regularly deified, and even in the Georgics (I. 34) Vergil speaks of the signs
        of the Zodiac crowding up to make room for Augustus. The sacrifice is further explained (<span class="link" onclick="refer('1.43')">43</span>)
        as being 12 days every year, evidently referring to the offerings on the first of every
        month to the household gods or Lares.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>meas errare boves permisit</text>
        <references>1.9.2--1.9.4, 1.10.5</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="link lt" onclick="refer('1.9.2--1.9.4, 1.10.5')">meas errare boves... permisit</span>, unusual poetic construction, acc. inf. after <span class="link lt" onclick="refer('1.10.5')">permitto</span>: the
        ordinary prose constr. is <span class="lt">ut</span> and subj. </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>ludere</text>
        <references>1.10.1</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="link lt" onlick="refer('1.10.1')">ludo</span>, often used half modestly for poetry: <span class="lt">
            carmina
            qui lusi pastorum
            </span> Georg. IV. 567; <span class="lt">iuvenilia lusi</span> Ov. Trist. v. 1, 7.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>formosam resonare doces Amaryllida siluas</text>
        <references>1.5.1--1.5.5</references>
        <comment>'teach the woodland to reecho the fair Amaryllis', i.e. the shepherd sings or calls
        upon his love, and the woods reecho the name.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>Amayillida</text>
        <references>1.5.4</references>
        <comment>The acc. <span class="lt">Amaryllida</span> is a kind of internal or extended cognate like <span class="lt">
            agere Antiopen,
            saltare Cyclopa, vox hominem sonat.
            </span>
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.6--1.10</references>
        <comment>6–10. Tit. Thanks to him to whom I shall always sacrifice as a god.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.11--1.19</references>
        <comment>Mel. I don't grudge it. There is trouble all over; I am tired, sick, driving my goats,
        one lately a mother: I ought to have known what that thunder meant!</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>usque adeo turbatur</text>
        <references>1.12.1--1.12.3</references>
        <comment>12. usque<span class="lt"> adeo </span>turbatur, 'such trouble there is', impers. pass. He is speaking of the
        suffering and confusion caused by the confiscation of the lands and allotment to the
        veterans. See introduction.

        The poor Meliboeus then (with a touch of dramatic pathos) laments his own troubles: he has
        to go on and on (<span class="lt">protenus</span>): he is sick and tired (<span class="lt">aeger</span>): one of his she goats he can hardly
        pull by a cord (<span class="lt">duco vix</span>) having left the new-born twin kids on the hard stones (<span class="lt">silice</span>).
        Then with rustic superstition he adds 'he might have known the coming trouble, from seeing
        the oaks struck by lightning'.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>protenus</text>
        <references>1.13.1</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">protenus</span>, 'on and on': expressing his weariness.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>1.14.1--1.15.8</text>
        <references></references>
        <comment>The goat had given birth to (<span class="lt">conixa</span> 'travailed' for the commoner <span class="lt">enixa</span>) two kids among
        the nut bushes on the stony soil. There is a touch of pity in a <span class="lt">silice in nuda</span>; the little
        things had to die, as they must be left behind: but they might at least have had soft moss
        or grass to die on!</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>si mens non laeva fuisset</text>
        <references>1.16.5--1.16.9</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">si mens non laeva fuisset</span>, elliptical use of the conditional common in all
        colloquial speech: he means 'I remember the prophecy and might have expected this misfortune
        had I not been blind'.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>de caelo tactas</text>
        <references>1.17.1--1.17.3</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">de caelo tactas</span>, 'struck from heaven', picturesque (perhaps augurial) phrase for
        lightning. Old authorities tell us that the striking of different trees portended different
        misfortunes, the oak being a sign of exile.
            <span class="lt">memini praedicere</span>, 'I remember that they foretold', the pres. inf. being the regular idiom
        when the thing remembered is part of the person's own experience, as here.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>da</text>
        <references>1.19.7</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">da</span>, 'tell': just as <span class="lt">accipio</span> is used both in prose and poetry for 'hear'.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.19</references>
        <comment>[Before this line a spurious verse '<span class="lt">saepe sinistra cava praedixit ab ilice cornix</span>' has
        got into the text from IX. 15.]</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.20--1.26</references>
        <comment>[20–26. Tit. I used to think Rome a small town like ours: it is quite big.]</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>1.20.1--1.20.6</text>
        <references></references>
        <comment>The dramatic colour is kept up. Tityrus tells his story in a roundabout rustic
        style.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>huic nostrae</text>
        <references>1.21.3--1.21.4</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">huic nostrae</span>, Mantua, near which (at the village of Andes) was Vergil's home.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>depellere</text>
        <references>1.22.4</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">depellere</span>, 'drive down' to 'our town' Mantua.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>sic canibus catulos similis, sic matribus haedos</text>
        <references>1.23.1--1.23-7</references>
        <comment>i.e. I thought Mantua was to Rome just as kids are to goats, puppies to dogs, or
        any other little things to big ones.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>lenta... uiburna</text>
        <references>1.26.2, 1.26.5</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">lenta viburna</span>, 'pliant osiers'.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.27--1.36</references>
        <comment>[27–36. M. What took you to Rome? Tit. To get freedom, now that I have left Galatea and
        love Amaryllis.]</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>Libertas; quae sera, tamen respexit inertem</text>
        <references>1.28.1--1.28.6</references>
        <comment>'Freedom, which though late has cast her eyes upon the sluggard'. A slave might buy his
        freedom: but as long as he was bound to his first love Galatea, he was slow (<span class="lt">iners</span>) to buy
        it, for all his savings were squandered. Now he has a new love Amaryllis, evidently more
        thrifty: so he has saved up and been to Rome to buy his freedom.
            <span class="lt">sera tamen respexit</span>, abridged neat phrase (like the Greek use with ὅμως) for 'though late,
        yet has looked upon me'.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>postquam... cadebat</text>
        <references>1.29.2, 1.29.5</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">postquam</span>, with imperfect (or present, 31) in its proper precise use, dating the
        beginning of the new habit or state of things.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>peculi</text>
        <references>1.33.7</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">peculi</span>, slaves were allowed to have private money, called <span class="lt">peculium</span>. They were also
        allowed to marry, (though not a legal recognised conubium): but Vergil is here thinking less
        of the life of Roman slaves and more of the free loves of Sicilian shepherds.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>pinguis</text>
        <references>1.35.1</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">pinguis</span>, 'rich': perhaps what we call cream-cheese; anyhow good of its kind.
        ingratae, playful indignation: the city did not pay him as much as he wanted for his
        cheeses.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.37--1.46</references>
        <comment>[37–46. M. I wondered why Amaryllis was so sad. Tit. I had to go. At Rome I saw the
        youth who gave me leave to stay on my land.]</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.37--1.38</references>
        <comment>Mel. playfully apostrophises the absent Amaryllis, who, in her sorrow for having to
        part from Tityrus, calls on the gods and leaves her apples ungathered.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.39--1.40</references>
        <comment>He tells Tityrus, with playful exaggeration, that not Amaryllis only, but the
        very springs and trees regretted his absence.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>aberat</text>
        <references>1.39.3</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">aberat</span>, a long. The <span class="lt">-at</span> of imperf. was originally long, and Vergil occasionally
        uses it so (tho' usually in a pause) from fondness for archaic forms. Ennius has '<span class="lt">ponebat
            ante salutem</span>': Plautus has it long. So G. IV. 137, A. V. 853, VII. 174 &amp;c.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>quid facerem?</text>
        <references>1.41.1--1.41.2</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">quid facerem?</span> past deliberative: 'what was I to do?'</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>praesentis</text>
        <references>1.42.3</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">praesentes</span>, idiomatically used, with gods, to mean 'powerful'. e.g. <span class="lt">
            praesentia numina
            Fauni
            </span> G. I. 10, <span class="lt">si quid praesentius audes</span> A. XII. 152, <span class="lt">praesentius auxilium</span> G. II. 127.
            <span class="lt">alibi</span> goes with both clauses, the sense being 'I had to go to Rome, for nowhere else could I
        either &amp;c.'
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>iuvenem</text>
        <references>1.43.4</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">iuvenem</span>, Octavianus: the figure—the shepherd buying his freedom—is inextricably
        mixed up with the thing figured—the poet receiving his lands back from Augustus. The slave
        goes to Rome to buy his freedom; but when he gets there he sees not his master but Augustus;
        and instead of buying his freedom he receives permission not to leave his home.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>submittite</text>
        <references>1.46.6</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">submittite</span>, 'rear', the regular word, cf. Georg. III. 75, <span class="lt">
            in spem submittere
            gentis
            </span>.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.47--1.59</references>
        <comment>[47–59. M. Happy man, you will keep your farm, and, poor tho' the land be, you will be
        happy in the familiar life, the sights and sounds of the country.]</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.48</references>
        <comment>The sense is:—
        48. 'Tho' the bare rock mars all your pasture, and the swamp covers them with the muddy
        rush', obducat being more appropriate to the last sentence, in which it occurs—the figure
        zeugma.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>graves... fetas</text>
        <references>1.50.3, 1.50.6</references>
        <comment>graves fetas, 'the pregnant ewes'.
        [fetus also means 'having given birth' and some take it so here translating graves
        'weakly' 'slow': but the other is the proper meaning of gravis, and fetus too. So A. 11.
        237, <span class="lt">machina feta armis</span>, of the wooden horse with soldiers inside.]
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.52--1.59</references>
        <comment>This pretty passage shews well Vergil's inborn love of the country.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>frigus... opacum</text>
        <references>1.53.4, 1.53.6
        </references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">frigus opacum</span>, 'the cool shade'; sacros, as every spring or rill had its god, or
        nymph.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>quae semper</text>
        <references>1.54.3--1.54.4</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">quae semper</span>, 'as ever', 'as of old', <span class="lt">ab limite</span>, 'on the border', like span.lt.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>Hyblaeis apibus florem depasta salicti</text>
        <references>1.55.1--1.55.5</references>
        <comment>'its willow blossom rifled by the Hyblaean bees'.
            <span class="lt">Hyblaeis</span>, the bees of Hybla in Sicily were famous, and this is what is called the
        'literary' use of epithets: wine is called 'Massic' or 'Falernian', marble is 'Parian', the
        arrow is 'Cydonian', the bow is 'Parthian', &amp;c. not so much to specify the kind, as to
        remind the reader of the Greek poets who speak of them.        
            <span class="lt">florem depasta</span>, might be acc. of respect; but considering Vergil's usage, it is much more
        probably the Greek use of acc. of the object after the perf. passive, really an elastic
        extension of the active construction to the passive voice.
        Thus the Greeks say:
        Active
        ἐπιτρέπω σοὶ τὴν ἀρχήν
        ἐγγράφω τῇ δέλτῳ ξυνθήματα
        Passive
        ἐπιτέτραψαι τὴν ἀρχήν
        δέλτος ἐγγεγραμμένη ξυνθήματα
        This usage the Roman poets imitated, as well as the acc. after the middle, which they very
        likely did not distinguish from the other. Other instances of the acc. after passive are
            <span class="lt">fusus barbam</span> A. X. 838: <span class="lt">inscripti nomina regum</span> Ecl. ΙΙΙ. 106: <span class="lt">per pedes traiectus lora</span> A.
        ΙΙ. 272: <span class="lt">caesariem effusae</span> G. IV. 337: <span class="lt">caeruleos implexae crinibus angues</span> G. IV. 482.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.56</references>
        <comment>
        56. Notice the soothing whispering sound, produced by the sibilants and liquids, to imitate
        or suggest the thing described. So Tennyson's famous lines in the Princess:
        'The moan of doves in immemorial elm
        and murmur of innumerable bees.'
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>frondator</text>
        <references>1.57.6</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">frondator</span>, the 'pruner' or 'dresser' had much to do, we are told in Georg. II.
        397—419: he clipped the bushes and willows, 'leafed' the elms to let the sun in on the
        grapes, pruned the vines, and plucked leaves for fodder.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>palumbes</text>
        <references>1.58.7</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">palumbes</span>. Mr Fowler, in his careful chapter on the Birds of Vergil, identifies
        the <span class="lt">palumbes</span> with two species, the wood-pigeon and the stock-dove: 'Perhaps the stock-dove
        is the more likely of the two to have been the bird generally meant: but it is quite
        possible that Romans confounded the two species' (A year with the birds, p. 115).</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>turtur</text>
        <references>1.59.5</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">turtur</span> is the turtle-dove: 'it is still found in small numbers passing the summer
        and breeding in Italy, and is most frequent in the subalpine region of which Vergil is here
        writing' (ib. p. 113).</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.60--1.64</references>
        <comment>[60–64. Tit. Beasts shall leave their element, and barbarians their home, ere I forget
        Octavianus.]</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>perratis amborum finibus</text>
        <references>1.62.2--1.62.4</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">perratis amborum finibus</span>, 'roaming each o'er the other's lands', phrase slightly
        strained, but meaning clear. The Parthian shall wander to the German frontier, the German to
        Parthia.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>Ararim</text>
        <references>1.63.2</references>
        <comment>The Arar (Saône) rises in the Vosges mountains in the E. of France, on the borders
        of Germany.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>labatur</text>
        <references>1.64.4</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">labatur</span>, common subj. with <span class="lt">antequam</span>, of anything which is prevented.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.65--1.84</references>
        <comment>[65–end. M. I shall go to the ends of the earth: shall I ever see my poor home again? a
        brutal soldier perhaps in possession! this is the result of civil war. Farewell: poor goats,
        come away! Tit. You might at least stay one more night and feast with me.]</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <references>1.65--1.67</references>
        <comment>65–67. We shall be scattered to the ends of the earth, some here, some there.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>Oaxen</text>
        <references>1.66.7</references>
        <comment>The Oaxes of Crete is not known as a river, but there is a town called Axus or Oaxus,
        and Vergil's river is doubtless named from this.
        There is no need to suspect or emend the reading.
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>Britannos</text>
        <references>1.67.6</references>
        <comment>The Britons are 'parted far from all the world' as being the most northerly country
        then known, and often proverbially mentioned as remote.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>post aliquot mea regna uidens mirabor aristas?</text>
        <references>1.70.1--1.70.7</references>
        <comment>'At last behold with wonder a few scant ears, my realm of old'. <span class="lt">post</span> resumes <span class="lt">
            longo post
            tempore: regna
            </span> is playfully pathetic exaggeration for the poor farm he loved: <span class="lt">aliquot</span>,
        either because the land is poor, or because he thinks the new possessor (a soldier) will
        spoil by ignorance and carelessness his land.
            <div>This is the best way of taking a rather artificially expressed and obscure line.</div>
        </comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>impius... miles...</text>
        <references>1.71--1.72</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">impius… miles</span> and <span class="lt">discordia cives</span> shew that he traces all this misery to the
        wicked civil wars of recent years.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>his</text>
        <references>1.73.3</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">his</span>, indignant, 'is it for these?"</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>pendere</text>
        <references>1.77.2</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">pendere</span>, 'leaning', vividly describes the goat perched on its ledge and reaching
        out to browse.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>cytisus</text>
        <references>1.79.2</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">cytisus</span>, 'lucerne' or shrubby clover.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <text>poteras</text>
        <references>1.80.5</references>
        <comment>
            <span class="lt">poteras</span>, he means 'you can': but the past is one of the delicacies of speech
        putting the offer as tho' the other's resolve was taken: 'you might have rested...'.</comment>
        <source>Sidgwick 1901</source>
    </entry>
</root>